<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="proofing/bc-framework.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="full" xml:lang="en">
                    <title type="main">THE NATURAL HISTORY OF CAROLINA, FLORIDA and the BAHAMA ISLANDS</title>
                    <title type="sub"> Containing the FIGURES of BIRDS, BEASTS, FISHES, SERPENTS, INSECTS, and PLANTS:
                        Particularly, the FOREST-TREES, SHRUBS, and other PLANTS, not hitherto described, Or very incorrectly
                        figured by Authors. Together with their DESCRIPTIONS in English and French. To which, are added
                        OBSERVATIONS on the AIR, SOIL, and WATERS: With Remarks upon AGRICULTURE, GRAIN, PULSE, ROOTS, &amp;C. To
                        the whole, Is Perfixed a new and correct Map of the Countries Treated of. </title>
                    <title type="sub">By the late MARK CATESBY, F.R.S. Revis’d by Mr. EDWARDS of the Royal College of Physicians,
                        London.</title>
                    <title level="m">VOL. 1</title>
                </title>
                <title type="full" xml:lang="fr">
                    <title type="main"> HISTOIRE NATURELLE de La CAROLINE, de la FLORIDE, &amp; des Iles de BAHAMA</title>
                    <title type="sub">Contenant les DESSEINS Des OISEAUX, des ANIMAUX, des POISSONS, des SERPENS, des INSECTES,
                        &amp; des PLANTES, quo se trouvent dans dex pays là; &amp; en particulier, des ARBRES des Fôrets,
                        Arbisseaux, &amp; autre Plantes, qui n’ont point été déscrits jusques à present par les Auteurs, ou qui on
                        été peu exactement dessinés. Avec leus DESCRIPTIONS en François &amp; en Anglois. A quoi on a ajoûté Des
                        Observations, sur l’AIR, le SOL, &amp; les EAUX, Avec des Remarques sur l’Agriculture, les Grains, les
                        Légumes, les Racines, &amp;c. Le tout est précédé d’une CARTE nouvelle &amp; exacte des Pays dont ils
                        s’agît. </title>
                    <title type="sub"> Par Feu Monsieur MARC CATESBY, de la Société Royale. Et revu par Monseiur EDWARDS, du
                        College Royal des Médecins de Londres. </title>
                    <title level="m">TOME 1</title>
                </title>
                <author>MARK CATESBY, F.R.S.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <availability>
                    <p>Mark Catesby’s Natural History is in the Public Domain. This expression of his work in TEI-XML, and the
                        associated stylesheets, are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported
                        License.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>December, 2012</date>
                <publisher>Botanica Caroliniana, Furman University, Department of Classics: folio.furman.edu</publisher>
                <authority>A digital edition with limited semantic markup, edited from public-domain images of Catebsy’s volume
                    provided by archive.org. Part of the Botanical Caroliniana project, a collaboration of Furman University’s
                    Department of Classics and the South Carolina Botanical Garden, Clemon University. Amy Hackney Blackwell and
                    Christopher Blackwell, edd.</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Catesby, F.R.S</author>
                        <title>THE NATURAL HISTORY OF CAROLINA, FLORIDA and the BAHAMA ISLANDS</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Printed for C. Marsh, in Round Court in the Strand; T. Wilcox, over against the New Church,
                                in the Strand.</publisher>
                            <date>1754</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div n="Ded" type="section">
                <div n="HRM" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Text">
                        <p n="H">To the Queen.</p>
                        <p n="1">Madam.</p>
                        <p n="2">As these Volumes contain an Essay towards the Natural History of that Part of Your MAJESTY’S
                            Dominions, which is particularly honoured by bearing your August Name CAROLINA, this and Your great
                            Goodness in encouraging all Sorts of Learning, have embolden’d me to implore Your Royal Protection and
                            Favour to my slender Performance. I hope your MAJESTY will not think a few MINUTES disagreeably spent,
                            in casting an EYE on these Leaves; which exhibit no contemptible Scene of Glorions Works of the
                            Creator, displayed in the New World; and hitherto lain concealed from the View of YOUR MAJESTY as well
                            as of YOUR Royal Predecessors, tho’ so long possessed of a Country, inferior to none of YOUR MAJESTY’S
                            American Dominions. </p>
                        <p n="3">Wherefore I esteem it a singular Happiness, after several Years Travel and Enquiry in so remote
                            Parts (by the generous Encouragement of several of Your MAJESTY’S Subjects, eminent for their Rank and
                            for their being Patrons of Learning) that I am the first that has had an opportunity of presenting to
                            a QUEEN of GREAT BRITIAN a Sample of the hitherto unregarded, tho’ beneficial and beautiful
                            Productions of YOUR MAJESTY’S DOMINIONS.</p>
                        <p n="4"> I am, May it please YOUR MAJESTY, Your MAJESTY’s Most humble, And most dutiful Subject M.
                            CATESBY.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div n="HRH" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Text">
                        <p n="H">To Her Royal Highness the Princess of WALES</p>
                        <p n="1">Madam,</p>
                        <p n="2">One of the most wonderful Production of <emph>America</emph> have now the Honour to lay
                            themselves at the Feet of your ROYAL HIGHNESS; Things new and strange to the Inhabitants of this Side
                            of the Globe; and which ust therefore necessarily excite, in Minds of infinitely less Discernment and
                            Piety than that of your ROYAL HIGHNESS, exaulted and religious Sentiments of Power, Wisdom, and
                            Goddness of that Almighty Being, who not only formed the Universe, but has adorned every Part of it
                            with an inconceivable Variety of Beauty and Magnificence.</p>
                        <p n="3">It was in Obedience to the Commands of our late <emph>most Gracious QUEEN</emph>, who
                            condescended to over-look ant approve my Drawings of the most Extraodrinary Curiosities of Nature
                            observable in <emph>Carolina</emph>, and the adnacent Countries subject to the Crown of <emph>Great
                                Britain</emph>, that I applied myself to compile a <title level="m">Natural History</title> of
                            those Parts of the World; and Her Majesty was pleased to take the First Voume of this Work under Her
                            own <emph>Royal Patronage</emph>.</p>
                        <p n="4">Such and Instance of Goodness emboldened me to hope Your ROYAL HIGHNESS would vouchsafe the like
                            Honour to this Second and Last Volume; and I have so happy not only to obtain Pardon for my
                            Presumption, but likeise to find the utmost of my Ambition gratified, in the Leave you have been
                            pleased to grant me, of publishing my Labours under the Protection of Your <emph>Illustrious
                                Name</emph>.</p>
                        <p n="5">Happy is it for Knowledge, when Princes love it, and become its Patrons! That You, MADAM, may
                            long live to be so, adorning Your high Station with every Princely Virtue, and enjoying, together with
                            Your <emph>Royal</emph> CONSORT, Wealth, Honour, Power, Fame, the Affection of grateful Nations, and
                            every Worldly Blessing; and that the like Happiness may attend Your lovely Offspring, and be to
                            endless Ages perpetuated to their Posterity, is the fervent Prayer of,</p>
                        <p n="6">MADAM, Your ROYAL HIGHNESS’, Most dutiful, Most humble, And most devoted Servant, MARK
                            CATESBY.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Praef" type="section">
                <div n="Eng" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Text" xml:lang="en">
                        <p n="H">The PREFACE</p>
                        <p n="1">The early Inclination I had to search after Plants, and other Productions in Nature, being much
                            suppressed by my residing too remote from <emph>London</emph> the Center of all Science, I was
                            deprived of all Opportunities and Examples to excite me to a stronger Pursuit after those Things to
                            which I was naturally bent: yet my Curiosity was such, that not being content with contemplating the
                            Products of our own Country, I soon imbibed a passionate Desire of viewing as well the Animal as
                            Vegetable Productions in their Native Countries; which were Strangers to <emph>England</emph>.
                                <emph>Virginia</emph> was the Place (I having Relations there) suited most with my Convenience to
                            go to, where I arriv’d the 23d. of <emph>April</emph> 1712. I thought then so little of prosecuting a
                            Design of the Nature of this Work, that in the Seven Years I resided in that Country, (I am ashamed to
                            own it) I chiefly gratified my Inclination in observing and admiring the various Productions of those
                            Countries; only sending from thence some dried Specimens of Plants and some of the most Specious of
                            them in Tubs of Earth, at the Request of some curious Friends, amongst whom was Mr. <emph>Dale</emph>
                            of <emph>Braintree</emph> in <emph>Essex</emph>, a skilful Apothecary and Botanist: to him, besides
                            Specimens of Plants, I sent some few Observations on the Country, which he communicated to the late
                                <emph>William Sherard</emph>, L. L. D. one of the most celebrated Botanists of this Age, who
                            favoured me with his Friendship on my Return to <emph>England</emph> till the Year 1719; and by his
                            Advice, (tho conscious of my own Inability) I first resolved on this Undertaking, so agreeable to my
                            Inclination. But as Expences were necessary for carrying the Design, I here most gratefully
                            acknowledge the Assistance and Encouragement I received from several Noble Persons and Gentlemen,
                            whose Names are here undermention’d.</p>
                        <p n="2"><list>
                                <item>His Grace the Duke of CHANDOIS.</item>
                                <item>The Right Honourable THOMAS Earl of OXFORD.</item>
                                <item>The Right Honourable THOMAS Earl of MACCLESFIELD.</item>
                                <item>The Right Honourable JOHN Lord PERCIVAL.</item>
                                <item>Sir GEORGE MARKHAM, Bar F.R.S.</item>
                                <item>Sir HENRY GOODRICK, Bar.</item>
                                <item>Sir HANS SLOANE, Bar President of the Royal Society, and of the College of
                                    Physicians.</item>
                                <item>The Honourable Colonel FRANCIS NICHOLSON, Governor of <emph>South Carolina</emph>.</item>
                                <item>RICHARD MEAD, M. D. and F.R.S.</item>
                                <item>CHARLES DUBOIS, Esq. F.R.S.</item>
                                <item>JOHN KNIGHT, Esq; F.R.S.</item>
                                <item>WILLIAM SHERARD, L.L.D. and F.R.S.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p n="3">With this Intention, I set out again from <emph>England</emph>, in the Year 1722, directly for
                                <emph>Carolina</emph>; which Country, tho’ inhabited by <emph>English</emph> above an Age past,
                            and a Country inferior to none in Fertility, and abounding in Variety of the Blessings of Nature; yet
                            it’s Productions being very little known except what barely related to Commerce, such as Rice, Pitch
                            and Tar; was thought the most proper Place to search and describe the Productions of: Accordingly, I
                            arrived in <emph>Carolina</emph> 23d. of <emph>May</emph> 1722, after a pleasant tho’ not a short
                            Passage. In our Voyage we were frequently entertain’d with Diversions not uncommon in crossing the
                                <emph>Atlantick</emph> Ocean, as catching of Sharks, strikeing of Porpuses, Dolphins Bonetoes,
                            Albicores and other Fish; which three last we regaled on when Fortune favoured us in catching them;
                            and even the Flesh of Sharks and Porpuses would digest well with the sailors, when long fed on Salt
                            Meats. The Pursuit of Dolphins after Flying-Fish, was another Amusement we were often diverted with;
                            the Dolphins having raised the Flying-Fish, by the swiftness of their Swimming, keep Pace with them,
                            and pursue them so close that the Flying-Fish at length tired, and their Wings dry’d, and thereby
                            necessitated to drop in the Water, often fall into the Jaws of their Pursuers; at some Times neither
                            Element aford them Safety, for no sooner do they escape their Enemies in the Water, but they are
                            caught in the Air by voracious Birds. But what seem’d most remarkable of this Kind, was, that in the
                            Latitude of 26 Degrees North, about the Midway between the two Continents of <emph>Africa</emph> and
                                <emph>America</emph>, which I think cannot be less than 600 Leagues, an Owl appear’d hovering over
                            our Ship; these Birds have short Wings, and have been observed not to be capable of long Flights, it
                            being a common Diversion for Boys to run them down after the second or third Flight This Owl after
                            some Attempts to rest, disappear’d; and the same Day being the 22d. of <emph>March</emph>, an Hawk
                            with a white Head, Breast, and Belly, appear’d in like Manner, and the Day after, some Swallows
                            appear’d, but none ventur’d to alight on any Part of the Ship. No Birds seem more able to continue
                            long on their Wings, than Hawks and Swallows; but that an Owl should be able to hold out so long a
                            Flight, is to me most surprising. </p>
                        <p n="4">Upon my arrival at <emph>Charles Town</emph>, I waited on General <emph>Nicholson</emph>, then
                            Governour of that Province, who received me with much Kindness, and continued his Favours during my
                            stay in that Country. Nor Could I excuse my self of Ingratitude; without ackowledging the hospitable
                            and kind Entertainment I generally met with amongst the Gentlemen of the Country, which much
                            contributed to the Facilitating the Work I went about.</p>
                        <p n="5">As I arrived at the beginning of the Summer I unexpectedly found this Country possessed not only
                            with all the Animals and Vegetables of <emph>Virginia</emph>, but abounding with even a greater
                            Variety. The inhabited Parts of <emph>Carolina</emph> extend West from the Sea about 60 Miles, and
                            almost the whole Length of the Coast, being a level, low Country. In these Parts I continued the first
                            Year searching after, collecting and describing the Animals and Plants. I then went to the Upper
                            uninhabited Parts of the Country, and continued at and about <emph>Fort Moore</emph>, a small Fortress
                            on the Banks of the River <emph>Savannah</emph>, which runs from thence a Course of 300 Miles down to
                            the Sea, and is about the same Distance from ’its Source, in the Mountains.</p>
                        <p n="6">I was much delighted to see Nature differ in these Upper Parts, and to find here abundance of
                            Things not to be seen in the Lower Parts of the Country; this encouraged me to take several Journeys
                            with the <emph>Indians</emph> higher up the Rivers, towards the Mountains, which afforded not only a
                            Succession of new vegetable Appearances, but most delightful Prospects imaginable, besides the
                            Diversion of Hunting Buffello’s, Bears, Panthers, and other wild Beasts. In these Excursions I
                            employ’d an <emph>Indian</emph> to carry my Box, in which, besides Paper and Materials for Painting, I
                            put dry’d Specimens of Plants, Seeds, &amp;c. as I gather’d them. To the Hospitality and Assistance of
                            these Friendly <emph>Indians</emph>, I am much indebted, for I not only subsisted can what they shot,
                            but their First Care was to erect a bark hut, at the approach of rain to keep me any my Cargo from
                            wet.</p>
                        <p n="7">I shall next proceed to an account of the Method I have observed in giving the Natural History of
                            these Countries; to begin therefore with Plants, I had principally a regard to the Forest-Trees and
                            Shurbs, shewing their several mechanical and other Uses, as in Building, Joynery, Agriculture, Food,
                            and Medicine I have likewise taken notice of those Plants, that will bear our <emph>English</emph>
                            Climate, which I have experiences from what I have growing at Mr. <emph>Bacon</emph>’s, Sucessor of
                            the late Mr. <emph>Fairchild</emph> at <emph>Hoxton</emph>, where many have withstood the Rigour of
                            several Winters, without Protection, while other Plants, tho’ from the same Country, have perished for
                            Want of it.</p>
                        <p n="8">As there is a greater Variety of the feather’d Kind than of any other Animals (at least to be
                            come at) and as they excel in the Beauty of their Colours, and have a nearer relation to the Plants of
                            which they feed on and frequent; I was incuded chiefly (so far as I could)to compleat an Account of
                            them, rather than to describe promiscuously, Insects and other Animals; by which I must have omitted
                            many of the Birds (for I had not Time to do all); by which method I believe very few Birds have
                            escaped my knowledge, except some Water Fowl, and some of those which frequent the Sea.</p>
                        <p n="9">Of Beasts there are not many species diferent from those in the old World: most of these I have
                            figured, except those which do not materially differ from the same Species in <emph>Europe</emph>, and
                            those which have been described by other Authors.</p>
                        <p n="10">Of Serpents very few I believe have escaped me, for upon shewing my Designs of them to several
                            of the most intelligent Persons, many of them confess’d not to have seen them all, and none of them
                            pretended to have seen any other Kinds.</p>
                        <p n="11">Of Fish I have described not above Five nor Six from <emph>Carolina</emph>, deferring that Work
                            till my Arrival at the <emph>Bahama</emph> Islands; which as they afford but few Quadrupeds and Birds,
                            I had more Time to describe the Fishes, and tho’ I had been often told they were very remarkable, I
                            Was surprised to find how lavishly Nature had adorn’d them with <emph>Marks</emph> and
                                <emph>Colours</emph> most admirable.</p>
                        <p n="12">As for Insects these Countries abound in numerous kinds, but I was not able to delineate a great
                            Number of them for the Reasons already assign’d: After my Continuance almost three Years in
                                <emph>Carolina</emph> and the adjacent parts (which the <emph>Spaniards</emph> call
                                <emph>Florida</emph> particularly that Province lately honour’d with the name of
                                <emph>Georgia</emph> ) I went to <emph>Providence</emph>, one of the <emph>Bahama</emph> Islands;
                            to which Place I was invited by his Excellency <emph>Charles Phinney</emph>, Esq; Governour of these
                            Islands, and was entertain’d by him with much Hospitality and Kindness: From thence I visited many of
                            the adjacent Islands, particularly <emph>Ilathera</emph>, <emph>Andros</emph>, <emph>Abbacco</emph>
                            and other neighbouring Islands; tho’ these rocky Islands produce many fine Plants, which I have here
                            described; I had principally a Regard to the Fish, there being not any, or a very few of them
                            described by any Author: Both in <emph>Carolina</emph> and on these Islands, I made successive
                            Collections of dry’d Plants and Seeds, and at these Islands more particularly I coIlected many
                            Submarine productions, as Shells, Corallines, <emph xml:lang="la">Fruitices Marini</emph>, Sponges,
                                <emph xml:lang="la">Astroites</emph>, &amp;c. These I imparted to my curious Friends, more
                            particularly (as I had the greatest Obligations) to that great Naturalist and promoter of Science Sir
                                <emph>Hans Sloane</emph>, Bart. to whose goodness I attribute much of the Success I had in this
                            Undertaking.</p>
                        <p n="13">As I was not bred a Painter I hope some faults in Perspective, and other Niceties, may be more
                            readily excused, for I humbly conceive Plants, and other Things done in a Flat, tho’ exact manner, may
                            serve the Purpose of Natural History, better in some measure than in a more bald and Painter like Way.
                            In designing the Plants, I always did them while fresh and just gather’d: And the Animals, paricularly
                            the Birds, I painted them while alive (except a very few) and gave them their Gestures pecu1iar to
                            every kind of Bird, and where it would admit of, I have adapted the Birds to those Plants on which
                            they fed, or have any Relation to. Fish which do not retain their Colours when out of their Element, I
                            painted at different times, having a succession of them procur’d while the former lost their Colours:
                            I dont pretend to have had this advantage in all, for some kinds I saw not plenty of, and of others I
                            never saw above one or two: Reptiles will live many Months without Sustenance, so that I had no
                            difficulty in Painting them while living.</p>
                        <p n="14">At my return from <emph>America</emph>, in the Year 1726, I had the satisfaction of having my
                            Labours approved of, and was honour’d with the Advice of several of the above-mention’d Gentlemen,
                            most skill’d in the Learning of Nature who were pleased to think them worth Publishing, but that the
                            Expence of Graving would make it too burthensome an Undertaking, this Opinion, from such good Judges,
                            discouraged me from attemping it any further: And I alter’d my Design of going to <emph>Paris</emph>
                            or <emph>Amsterdam</emph> where I at first proposed to have them done. At length by the kind Advice
                            and Instructions of that inimitable Painter Mr. <emph>Joseph Goupy</emph>, I undertook and was
                            initiated in the way of Etching them myself, which tho’ I may not have done in a Graver-like manner,
                            choosing rather to omit their method of cross-Hatching, and to follow the humour of the Feathers,
                            which is more laborious, and I hope has proved more to the purpose.</p>
                        <p n="15">The Illuminating Natural History is so particularly Essential to the perfect understanding of
                            it, that I may aver a clearer Idea may be conceiv’d from the Figures of Animals and Plants in their
                            proper Colours, than from the most exact Description without them: Wherefore l have been less prolix
                            in the Discription, judging it unnecessary to tire the Reader with Describing every Feather, yet I
                            hope sufficient to distinguish them without Confusion.</p>
                        <p n="16">As to the Plants I have given them the <emph>English</emph> and <emph>Indian</emph> Names they
                            are known by in these Countries: And for the Latin Names I was beholden to the above-mention’d Learned
                            and accurate Botanist Dr. <emph>Sherard</emph>. </p>
                        <p n="17">Very few of the Birds having Names assign’d them in the Country, except some which had Indian
                            Names; I have call’d them after European Birds of the same Genus, with an additional Epithet to
                            distinguish them. As the Males of the Feather’d Kind (except a very few) are more elegantly colour’d
                            than the Females, I have throughout exhibited the Cocks only, except two or three; and have added a
                            short Description of the Hens, which they differ in colour from the Cocks, the want of which Method
                            has caused great Confusion in works of this Nature. </p>
                        <p n="18">Of the Paints, particularly Greens, used it the Illumination of Figures, I had principally a
                            regard to those most resembling Nature, that were durable and would retain their Lustre, rejecting
                            others very specious and shining, but of an unnatural Colour and fading Quality: Yet give me leave to
                            observe there is no Degree of Green but what some Plants are possess’d of at different Timesof the
                            Year, and the same Plant changes it’s Colour gradually with its Age, for in the Sping the Woods and
                            all Plants in General are more Yellow and bright, and as the Summer advances the Greens grow deeper,
                            and the nearer their Fall are yet of a more dark and dirty Colour. What I infer from thisis that by
                            comparing a Painting with a living Plant, the difference of Colour, if any may proceed from the
                            above-mention’d Cause.</p>
                        <p n="19">As to the <emph>French</emph> Translation I am oblig’d to a very ingenious Gentleman, a Doctor
                            of Physick, and a <emph>Frenchman</emph> born, whose Modesty will not permit me to mention his
                            Name.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div n="Fra" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Text" xml:lang="fr">
                        <p n="H">PREFACE</p>
                        <p n="1">L’Inclination que je sentois dès ma jeunesse à rechercher la connoissance des Plantes, &amp; des
                            autres production de la Nature, étoit fort traversée par mon éloignement de <emph>Londres</emph>, le
                            centre de toutes les Sciences: j’ étois privé par là des occasions, &amp; des exemples qui auroient pu
                            m’exciter à suivre mon panchant avec plus d’ardeur. Cependant il étoit tel, que l’étude &amp; la
                            contemplation des productions de la Nature, que l’<emph>Angleterre</emph> me fournissoit, ne
                            satisfaisant point ma curiosité, je conçus une envie passionnée d’aller voir dans leurs propres
                            climats les Plantes &amp; les Animaux qui étoient étrangers à ma patrie. La <emph>Virginie</emph>
                            étoit le pays où je pouvois aller le plus commodément, à 23 d’<emph>Avril</emph> 1712. Je songeois si
                            peu dans ce tems là à entreprendre un ouvrage tel que celui que je donne au Public, que pendant les
                            sept années que je restai dans ce pays, j’avoue à ma bonte que je ne m’ occupai qu’ à en observer
                            &amp; admirer les productions, sans autre invention que de satisfaire mon goût: sulement j’envoyois
                            des plantes desséchées, &amp; quelques unes des plus belles dans des pots, à quelques curieux de mes
                            amis que m’en avoient prié. Mr. <emph>Dale</emph> de <emph>Braintree</emph> en la Province
                                d’<emph>Essex</emph>, habile Apotiquaire &amp; Botaniste, étoit de ce nombre; mais outre des
                            plantes desséchées, je lui envoyai quelques observations sur le pays. Il les communiqua à feu Mr.
                                <emph>Guillaume Sheerard</emph>, un des plus fameux Botanistes de ce Siecle, qui me fit l’honneur
                            de me recevoir au nombre de ses amis, lorsque je fus de retour en Angleterre en 1719. Ce fut par son
                            avis que je résolus de commencer cette entreprise très conforme à mon inclination, malgré le peu de
                            capacité que je me trouvois; mais comme l’exécution de ce dessein exigeoit beaucoup de dépense, c’est
                            avec plaisir &amp; une extrême réconnaissance que je déclare ici que j’ai été aidé à la soutenir par
                            la générosité de plusieurs Seigneurs &amp; autres dont je joins ici les noms;</p>
                        <p n="2">
                            <list>
                                <item>Milord Duc de <emph>Chanois</emph>.</item>
                                <item>Milord Comte <emph>d’Oxford</emph>.</item>
                                <item>Milord Comte de <emph>Macclesfield</emph>.</item>
                                <item>Milord <emph>Percival</emph>.</item>
                                <item>Le Chevalier <emph>Markham</emph>, Membre de la Societé Royale.</item>
                                <item>Le Chevalier <emph>Goodrick</emph>.</item>
                                <item> Le Chevalier <emph>Hans Sloane</emph>, Président de la Societé Royale, &amp; du College des
                                    Médecins.</item>
                                <item>Le Colonel <emph>Nicholson</emph>, Gouverneur de la Caroline Méridionalle.</item>
                                <item> Mr. <emph>Mead</emph>, Docteur en Médecine, &amp; Membre de la Societé Royale.</item>
                                <item>Mr. <emph>Du Bois</emph>, Membre de la Societé Royale.</item>
                                <item> Mr. <emph>Knight</emph>, Membre de la Societé Royale.</item>
                                <item>Mr. <emph>Sherard</emph>, Docteur en Droit, &amp; Membre de la Societé Royale.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">Je partis dans ce dessein d’ Angleterre pour la Caroline en 1722. Quoi que ce pays soit habité
                            par les Anglois depuis plus d’un siecle, &amp; qu’il ne le cede à aucun autre par l’abondance &amp;
                            les variétés des productions dont la nature l’a enrichi, cependant on n’en connoit gueres que ce qui
                            entre dans le commerce, comme le ris, la poix, &amp; le goudron; c’est ce qui me détermina à m’y
                            fixer, pour en étudier &amp; décrire l’histoire naturelle. J’y arrivai le 23 de May 1722, après un
                            passage fort agréable, quoi qu’un peu long. Pendant le voyage nous primes souvent des plaisirs qui se
                            présentent ordinairement en traversant l’Océan: nous primes des requins, nous harponames des
                            marsouins, des dauphins, des bonites, des albicores, &amp; d’autres poissons. Quand nous avions le
                            bonheur d’en attraper des trois dernieres fortes, nous ne manquions pas de nous en régaler; &amp; les
                            matelots ne laissoient pas de s’accommoder de la chair de marsouins &amp; de requins, lorsqu’ils
                            n’avoient vécu pendant long tems que de viandes salées. Un autre de nos amusements étoit de voir la
                            chasse des dauphins après les poissons volans: les dauphins obligent les Poissons volans à s’élever
                            hors de l’eau; mais comme ils nagent aussi víte que les autres volent, ils les poursuivent de si près,
                            que les poissons volants lassés à fin, &amp; obligés de se replongere dans l’eau, parceque leurs ailes
                            déssechées ne les peuvent plus soutenir, tombent souvent dans la gueule de leurs ennemis; quelquesois
                            ils ne trouvent leur sureté ny dans l’un ny dans l’autre Element, car si tôt qu’ils s’echapent des
                            Poissons qui les poursuivent dans l’eau, ils sont pris dans l’Air par des Oiseaux de proye. Mais ce
                            qui nous parut de plus singulier en ce genre, ce fut qu’en la latitude de 26 Degrés vers le Nord,
                            environ au milieu des deux Continents de l’Afrique &amp; de l’Amérique, qui je crois ne peut pas être
                            moins eloigné des Terres que de 600 lieües, nous vimes un Hibou volant au dessus de nótre Vaisseau:
                            Ces oiseaux ont les ailes courtes, &amp; l’on remarque qu’ils ne peuvent pas voler fort loin; les
                            Enfants méme se divertissent à les lasser à quoi ils reüssissent après la seconde ou troisieme fois
                            qu’ils les ont fait partir. Ce Hibou disparut après avoir fait quelques tentatives pour se reposer. Et
                            le même jour, qui etoit le 22 de May, un Epervier, avec la tête, la poitrine &amp; le ventre blancs,
                            parut de la même maniere; nous vimes aussi quelques Hirondelles, mais nul ne se hazarda de se reposer
                            sur aucun endroit du Navire. Il n’ya a point d’Oiseaux qui semblent pouvoir se soutenir plus long tems
                            sur leurs ailes, que l’Epervier &amp; l’Hirondelle, mais qu’un Hibou ait été capable de continuer son
                            vol pendant si long tems, c’est ce qui me semble fort surprennant. </p>
                        <p n="4">A mon arrivée à Charles-town, je rendis mes devoirs au Géneral <emph>Nicholson</emph>, qui étoit
                            alors Gouverneur de la Province; il me reçut avec beaucoup de bonté, &amp; continua de metraiter de
                            même pendant mon sejour en ce païs, Je ne pourrois me disculper d’ingratitude, si je ne temoignois me
                            reconeoissance de l’hospitalitè, &amp; des manieres honnêtes que j’ai trouveèes dans la plus part des
                            principaux Habitans, ce qui facilita beaucoup mon dessein.</p>
                        <p n="5">Comme j’arrivai tout au commencement de l’Eté, je trouvai, contra mon attente, que ce pais avoit
                            non seulement tous les Animaux &amp; Végétaux de la Virginie, mais én avoit même une plus grande
                            varieté. La Partie de la Caroline qui est habitée s’étend depuis la Mer vers le Couchant environ 60
                            milles, &amp; presque toute la longueur de la Cóte; c’est un pain bas &amp; uni. J’y demeurai la
                            premiere année, m’occupant à chercher, à ramasser &amp; à décrire les Animaux &amp; les Plantes.
                            Ensuite j’avancai dans la partie inhabitée, &amp; restai quelques mois au Fort Moore, ou aux Environs;
                            c’est une petite Forteresse située sur les Bords de la Riviere Savanna; Elle sait trois cent milles de
                            chemin de là jusques à la mer, &amp; en remontant à sa source dans les Montagnes il n’ya pas moin de
                            distance.</p>
                        <p n="6">J’étois charmé de trouver dans ces quartiers les productions de la Nature si différentes; &amp;
                            un infinité de choses, qui ne se rencontroient pas dans la partie basse de ces pays. Cela m’encouragea
                            à entreprendre plusieurs voyages avec les Indiens vers les montagnes en rémontant les rivieres, ou
                            j’eus le plaisir de voir successivement de nouveaux Phénomenes végétaux, &amp; des vûes les plus
                            charmantes que l’imagination se puisse former, outre le divertissement de la chasse des buffles, des
                            sangliers, des pantheres, &amp; d’autres bêtes sauvages. Dans ces courses je me servois d’un Indien
                            pour porter une cassete, dans laquelle, outre du papier &amp; ce qui est nécessaire pour dessiner, je
                            mettois des Plantes desséchées, des Graines, &amp; tout ce que je ramassois. Je dois beaucoup à
                            l’hospitalité, &amp; à l’assistance des ces Indiens; car outre que je vivois de leur chasse, leur
                            prémier soin, si tôte que l’on étoit ménacé de pluie, étoit de me faire en diligence, une hutte
                            d’écorce, pour me mettre à couvert avec ma cargaison.</p>
                        <p n="7">Je vais à présent rendre compte de la méthode que j’ai suivie en composant l’histoire naturelle
                            de ces Pays, que je donne au Public; &amp; pour commencer par les Plantes, je me suis surtout attaché
                            aux Arbres des forêts, &amp; aux Arbrisseaux; j’ai fait voir leurs différens usages mécaniques &amp;
                            autres pour les bâtiments, les ouvrages de Menuiserie, l’Agriculture, la nourriture des hommes, &amp;
                            des Animaux, &amp; la Médicine. J’ai aussi remarqué les Plantes qui souffrent le climat d’Angleterre,
                            ce que j’ai connu par l’expérience en observant ce qui se passe dans le jardin de Mr.
                                <emph>Bacon</emph>, successeur de feu Mr. <emph>Fairchild</emph> à Hoxton, où Plusieurs de ces
                            Plantes ont résisté à la rigueur de plusieurs Hives, quoi qu’exposées en plein air, tandis que
                            d’autres du même pays, sont mortes, parce qu’elles n’étoient pas garanties du froid.</p>
                        <p n="8">La grande variété des Oiseaux, (qui passe de beaucoup celle des autres Animaux, du moins de ceux
                            que l’on peut attraper) la beauté des couleurs dont leur plumage est orné, &amp; le rapport qu’ils ont
                            le plus souvent avec les plantes dont ils se nourrissent, ou qu’ils fréquentent; tout cela m’engagea à
                            en faire, autant qu’ils me seroit possible, une description complette, plutôt que de donner pesle
                            mesle celles des Insectes &amp; d’autres Animaux: ce qui m’auroit obligé d’omettre plusieurs Oiseaux,
                            car je n’avons pas le temps de tout faire. De cette manière je crois que peu d’Oiseaux m’ont échappé,
                            excepté quelques Oiseaux aquatiques, &amp; quelques uns de chaux qui fréquentent la Mer.</p>
                        <p n="9">Pour les Quadrupedes, il n’y en a que peu d’espèces différentes de celles qui se trouvent dans le
                            vieux Monde: j’en ai dessiné la plus grande partie, hors ceux qui ne different pas beaucoup de la même
                            espèce en Europe, ou chaux qui ont été décrits par d’autres Auteurs.</p>
                        <p n="10">Je pense que très peux de Serpens m’ont échappé; car en faisant voir mes desseins à un grand
                            nombre de personnes très intelligentes en ces matières, plusieurs m’ont avoué qu’ils ne les avouent
                            pas tous vûs auparavant, &amp; personne n’a prétendu en connaître d’autres espèces.</p>
                        <p n="11">Je n’ai pas décrit plus de cinq ou six espèces de Poissons de la Caroline: je renvoyai ce
                            travail jusque’`a mon arrivée aux îles Bahama: on ny’y torve que peu d’Oiseaux &amp; d’Animaux à
                            quatre liés, ainsi je comtois y avoir plus de temps pour décrire les Poissons; &amp; quoi qu’on m’eut
                            prévenu su leur beauté singuliere je ne laissai pas d’être surpris, en voyant avec quelle profusion la
                            Nature les a ornés de couleurs &amp; de taches, dont l’éclat mérite la plus grande admiration.</p>
                        <p n="12">Ces pays abondent en différentes espèces d’Insectes; mais le raisons, que j’ai déjà reportées,
                            m’ont empêché d’en dessiner un grand nombre. Après avoir été pendant près de trois ans à la Caroline,
                            &amp; aux environs, particulièrement dans cette Province qu’on a honorée du nom de Georgie (que les
                            Espagnols appellent la Floride) j’allai à la Providence, qui est une des îles Bahama; j’y avoir été
                            invitée par son Excellence Mr. <emph>Charles Phinney</emph>, Gouverneur de ces îles, qui me reçut chez
                            lui, &amp; m’y retint pendant tout mon séjour avec beaucoup de bonté. De là je visitai plusieurs des
                            îles voisines, en particulier Ilathere, Andros, Abbaco, &amp; quelques autres des environs. Quoi que
                            ces îles pleines de rochers, produisent plusieurs Plantes très curieuses, que j’ai décrites ici, je
                            m’attachai principalement aux Poissons, parce qu’il n’y en a aucun, ou du moins très peu qui ayant été
                            décrits par les Auteurs. A la Caroline &amp; dans ces îles je fis successivement des collections de
                            Plantes desséchées &amp; de Semences; &amp; sur tout dans ces îles je ramassai plusieurs productions
                            de la Mer, comme des Coquilles, des Coraux, des Arbrisseaux marin, des Eponges, des Astroites, &amp;c.
                            J’en ai fait présent à quelques curieux de mes Amis, &amp; sur tout, ainsi que j’y étais obligé, à ce
                            grand Naturaliste, &amp; Patron des Sciences, Mr. le Chevalier <emph>Sloane</emph>, car j’avoue que
                            c’est à sa bonté que je suis redevable du succès, que j’ai eu dans cette entreprise.</p>
                        <p n="13">Je ne suis pas peintre de profession, ainsi j’espere qu’on excusera plus aisément quelques
                            fautes de Perspective, &amp; quelques autres finesses de l’Art, où j’ai peut-être manqué; car il me
                            semble que les Plantes, ou les autres choses que j’ai dessinées exactement, quoi que sans Perspective,
                            peuvent être aussi utilise pour l’Histoire naturelle, &amp; même plus, que si elles étoilent exprimées
                            plus hardiment, &amp; d’une manière plus pictoresque. J’ai toujours dessiné les Plantes toutes
                            fraiches, &amp; dans le moment qu’on venait de les cueillir, &amp; les Animaux, sur tout les Oiseaux,
                            pendant qu’ils étoilent vivants, excepté un très petit nombre; je leur ai donné à chacun son attitude
                            propre; &amp; autant qu’il a été possible, j’ai joint les Oiseaux aux Plantes desquelles ils se
                            nourrissent, ou aux-quelles ils ont quelque rapport. J’ai peint, à différentes reprises, les Poissons
                            qui perdent leurs couleurs, lorsqu’ils sont hors de l’eau: on m’en fournissait toûjours de nouveaux,
                            quand les autres ne pouvaient plus me servir; cependant je n’ai pas eu cette commodité pour tous, car
                            il y en a quelques espèces, que j’ai trouvées très rares, &amp; de quelques unes je n’ai vû qu’un ou
                            deux Poissons. Pour les Reptiles, comme ils vivent plusieurs mois sans manger, je n’ai trouvé aucune
                            difficulté à les peindre vivans.</p>

                        <p n="14">A mon retour de l’Amérique en l’année 1726, j’eus la satisfaction de voir mon travail approuvé;
                            &amp; plusieurs de ceux que j’ai nommés ci-dessus, gens très versés dans l’Histoire naturelle, m’
                            honorerent de leurs avis, &amp; jugeant que mon ouvrage méritait d’être publié, ils crurent que la
                            dépense de la gravure rendroit cette entreprise trop difficile. Ce sentiment quid venait de si bons
                            juges me découragea alors de la pousser plus loin, &amp; je quittai le dessein d’aller à Paris ou à
                            Amsterdam où j’avons projeté d’abord de faire graver mes desseins. Enfin, encouragé par les bons avis,
                            &amp; les instructions de cet inimitable Peintre Mr. <emph>Joseph Goupy</emph>, j’ai appris à les
                            graver moi même; &amp; quoi que je n’aie pas suivi la méthode des graveurs, qui est de hacher les
                            traits, aimant mieux suivre le trait des plumes, ce quid demande plus de travail, je me latte que ma
                            manière a mieux réussi pour mon dessein.</p>

                        <p n="15">Il est si nécessaire, pour bien entendre l’Histoire naturelle, d’enluminer les desseins qui en
                            représentent quelque partie, que je puis assûrer qu’on se formera une meilleure idée des Plantes,
                            &amp; des Animaux en les voyant représentés avec leurs couleurs naturelles que par la description la
                            plus exacte sans le secours des figures: c’est pourquoi je me suis moins étendu dans mes descriptions,
                            &amp; j’ai cru qu’il était inutile de fatiguer le Lecteur, en s’arrêtant sur chaque plume en
                            particulier; cependant j’espere en avoir assez dit pour les distinguer sans confusion.</p>

                        <p n="16">J’ai donné aux Plantes les noms Anglois &amp; Indiens, par lesquelles elles sont connues dans ce
                            pays là; &amp; le Dr. <emph>Sherard</emph>, ce savant &amp; exacte Botaniste, a eu la bonté de me
                            fournier les noms Latins.</p>

                        <p n="17">Comme dans le pays il y a peu d’Oiseau qui ayant des noms particuliers, excepté quelques uns qui
                            ont des noms Indiens, je leur ai donné ceux des Oiseaux Européens de la même espèce, avec un épithète
                            qui les distingue. Dans tout mon ouvrage, je n’ai représenté &amp; décrit que les mâles de chaque
                            espèce d’Oiseaux, parceque généralement leurs couleurs sont plus belles que celles des fémelles, hors
                            eux ou trois exemples où j’ai ajouté une courte descriptions de la fémelle, &amp; des couleurs qui la
                            distinguent du mâle: en négligeant cette méthode, il s’est glissé beaucoup de fautes dans les ouvrages
                            de ce genre.</p>

                        <p n="18">Dans le choix de couleurs, &amp; en particulier des verdes, pour enluminer les planches, j’ai
                            sur tout en attention à employer celles qui approchent le plus du naturel, qui sont les plus durables,
                            &amp; conservent le mieux leur lustre; &amp; j’ai rejetté les autres, quoi que brillantes &amp;
                            apparentes, mais peux naturelles, &amp; d’une qualité à se passer bientôt. Cependant qu’on me permette
                            de remarquer qu’il n’y a point de nuance de vers dont quelques Plantes ne soient colorées en
                            différents temps de l’année; &amp; la même Plante change sa couleur en vieillissant; car dans le
                            Printems les Plantes des Bois, &amp; toutes les Plantes en général, sont plus jaunes &amp; plus
                            brillantes, &amp; à mesure que l’Eté avance, le vers devient plus foncé, &amp; vers la rems de la
                            chute il est encore plus obscur &amp; plus sale; d’où je conclus que la différence de couleur, si on
                            en trouve, en comparant une Plante vivante avec sa représentation, peut procéder de la cause ci-dessus
                            mentionnée.</p>

                        <p n="19">Quant à la traduction Françoise, un de mes Amis, Docteur en Médecine, &amp; François, a bien
                            voulu s’en donner la peine, à condition qu’ils ne seroit pas nommé.</p>


                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
                <div n="Plate" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Figure">
                        <p n="Fig1">
                            <figure>
                                <figDesc facs="urn:cite:fufolioimg:Caroliniana.CatesbyNH1_13_t001">
                                    <ref facs="urn:cite:fufolioimg:Caroliniana.CatesbyNH1_13_t001:0.0413,0.0655,0.8775,0.8728">
                                        <caption> T.1 <foreign xml:lang="la">Aquila capite Albo.</foreign> The White headed Eagle.
                                        </caption>
                                    </ref>
                                    <ref facs="urn:cite:fufolioimg:Caroliniana.CatesbyNH1_13_t001:0.4625,0.4181,0.4563,0.5356">
                                        <caption>The Size of the Eagles head</caption>
                                    </ref>
                                </figDesc>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div n="Text" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Eng" xml:lang="en">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Aquila Capite Albo</foreign>: The Bald Eagle.</p>
                        <p n="1">This bird weighs nine pounds: the Iris of the eye white; over which is a prominence, cover’d with
                            a yellow skin; the Bill yellow, with the Sear of the same colour: the Legs and Feet are yellow; the
                            Tallons black; the Head and part of the Neck is white, as is the Tail; all the rest of the Body, and
                            Wings, are brown.</p>
                        <p n="2">Tho’ it is an Eagle of a small size, yet has great strength and spirit, preying on Pigs, Lambs,
                            and Fawns.</p>
                        <p n="3">They always make their Nests near the sea, or great rivers, and usually on old, dead Pine or
                            Cypress-trees, continuing to build annually on the same tree, till it falls. Tho' he is so formidable
                            to all birds, yet he suffers them to breed near his royal nest without molestation; particularly the
                            fishing and other Hawks, Herons, &amp;c. which all make their nests on high trees; and in some places
                            are so near one another, that they appear like a Rookery. This Bird is called the BALD EAGLE, both in
                            Virginia and Carolina, tho’ his head is as much feather’d as the other parts of his body.</p>
                        <p n="4">Both Cock and Hen have white Heads, and their other parts differ very little from one
                            another.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div n="Fra" xml:lang="fr">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Aquila Capite Albo</foreign>: Aigle à tête blanche.</p>
                        <p n="1">Cet oiseau pese neuf livres: l’iris de son oeil est blanche, au dessus de laquelle il y a une
                            avance couverte d’une peau jaune; le bec &amp; cette peau qui couvre la base de la mandibule
                            superieure est jaune, aussi bien que les jambes &amp; les piés; ses ongles sont noires, sa tête, &amp;
                            une partie de son col, de même que sa queüe, sont blanche; le reste du corps &amp; les ailes sont
                            brunes.</p>
                        <p n="2">Quoique ce soit une aigle d’une grandeur médiocre, elle a beaucoup de force &amp; de courage:
                            elle enleve de jeunes cochons, des agneaux, &amp; même des faons.</p>
                        <p n="3">Ces oiseaux sont toûjours leurs nids prés de la mer ou des fleuves, &amp; ordinairement sur un
                            vieux Pin ou sur un Cypres, &amp; les sont tous les ans sur le même arbre, jusqu’à ce qu’il tombe.
                            Quoique cette aigle soit très redoutable à tous les oiseaux, elle leur laisse cependant nourrir leurs
                            petits prés de son aire, sans les incommoder: c’est ce qu’elle fait sur tout à l’égard des faucons
                            pêcheurs, ou autres, des herons, &amp;c. qui sont tous leurs nids sur de grands arbres: on en voit
                            quelque fois si près les uns des autres que l’assemblage de ces nids paroit former une espece de
                            République. On appelle cet oiseau dans la Virginie &amp; dan la Caroline l”Aigle chauve, quoiqu’il y
                            ait sur sa tête autant de plumage que sur les autres parties de son corps.</p>
                        <p n="4">Le mâle &amp; la femelle ont tous deux la tête blanche; il n’y a qu’une trés-petite difference
                            entre les autres parties de leur corps.</p>

                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <div n="Plate" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Figure">
                        <p n="Fig2">
                            <figure>
                                <figDesc facs="urn:cite:fufolioimg:Caroliniana.CatesbyNH1_16_t002">
                                    <ref facs="urn:cite:fufolioimg:Caroliniana.CatesbyNH1_16_t002:0.085,0.0782,0.1163,0.0681">
                                        <caption> T.2 <foreign xml:lang="la">Accipter Piscatorious</foreign>: The Fishing Hawk.
                                        </caption>
                                    </ref>
                                </figDesc>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div n="Text" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Eng" xml:lang="en">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Accipter Piscatorious</foreign>: The Fishing Hawk.</p>
                        <p n="1">This Bird weighs three pounds and a quarter; from one end of the wing to the other extended, five
                            foot, five inches: the Bill is black, with a blue sear; the Iris of the eye yellow; the Crown of the
                            head brown, with a mixture of white feathers: from each Eye, backwards, runs a brown stripe; all the
                            upper part of the Back, Wing and Tail, dark-brown; the Throat, Neck and Belly, white: the Legs and
                            Feet are remarkably rough and scaly, and of a pale-blue colour; the Tallons black, and almost of an
                            equal size: the Feathers of the Thighs are short, and adhere close to them, contrary to others of the
                            Hawk kind; which nature seems to have designed for their more easy penetrating the water.</p>

                        <p n="2">Their manner of fishing is (after hovering a while over the water) to precipitate into it with
                            prodigious swiftness; where it remains for some minutes, and seldom rises without a fish: which the
                            Bald Eagle (which is generally on the watch) no sooner spies, but at him furiously he flies: the Hawk
                            mounts, screaming out, but the Eagle always soars above him, and compels the Hawk to let it fall;
                            which the Eagle feldom fails of catching, before it reaches the Water. It is remarkable, that whenever
                            the Hawk catches a Fish, he calls, as if it were, for the Eagle; who always obeys the call, if within
                            hearing.</p>

                        <p n="3">The lower parts of the Rivers and Creeks near the sea abound most with these Eagles and Hawks,
                            where these diverting contests are frequently seen.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div n="Fra" xml:lang="fr">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Accipter Piscatorious</foreign>: Faucon pêcheur.</p>
                        <p n="1">Cet oiseau pese trois livres &amp; un quart. Lorsque les ailes sont déployées il y a cinq piés
                            pouces depuis l’extremité de l’une, jusque’ à l’extremité de l’autre. Son bec est noir, &amp; la peau
                            qui couvre la base de la mandibule superieure est bleue, l’iris de l’oeil jaune, le sommet de la tête
                            est brun, avec un mélange de plumes blanches; il y a de chaque côté du cou une raye brune qui commence
                            auprès de l’oeil, &amp; qui s’allonge en arriere. Tout le dessus de son dos, aussi bien que ses ailes
                            &amp; sa queüe sont d’un brun foncé. Il a la gorge, le cou, &amp; le ventre blancs; ses jambes &amp;
                            ses mains sont couvertes d’une écaille raboteuse, d’un bleu pale: ses doigts sont noirs &amp; presque
                            d’une égale grandeur, &amp; au contraire des autres especes de Faucons, les plumes des cuisses de
                            ceux-ci sont courtes &amp; s’appliquent étroitement sur la peau, la nature les ayant ainsi disposées,
                            à ce qu’il paroît, afin que ces oiseaux pussent pénétrer plus aisément dans l’eau, ce qu’elle a refusé
                            aux autres especes de Faucons.</p>

                        <p n="2">Leur manier de pécher est celle-ci: après que le Faucon a plané quelque tems au dessus de l’eau,
                            il s’y précipite d’une vitesse surprenante, y reste quelques minutes, &amp; en sort rarement sans
                            poisson, ce que l’ Aigle, qui est ordinairement aux aguets, n’a pas plutôt apperçu quelle vient à lui
                            avec fureur; le Faucon s’éleve en poussant des cris, mais l’Aigle vole toujours au dessus de lui,
                            &amp; le force de lacher sa proye, qu’elle ne manque guéres d’attraper avant que cette proye tombe
                            dans l’eau. Il est à remarquer que toutes les fois que le Faucon prend un poisson, il appelle, pour
                            ainsi dire, l’Aigle, qui obéit toujours si elle est à portée de l’entendre.</p>

                        <p n="3">Le bas des rivieres &amp; les petites bayes de la mer sont des lieux frequentés par cette forte
                            d’Aigles &amp; de Faucons: on y voit souvent leurs disputes, qui sont assez divertissantes.</p>



                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div n="3" type="section">
                <div n="Plate" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Figure">
                        <p n="Fig3">
                            <figure>
                                <figDesc facs="urn:cite:fufolioimg:Caroliniana.CatesbyNH1_17_t003">
                                    <ref facs="urn:cite:fufolioimg:Caroliniana.CatesbyNH1_17_t003:0.75,0.0832,0.13,0.0915">
                                        <caption> T.3 <foreign xml:lang="lat">Accipiter Palumbarius</foreign> The Pigeon Hawk —
                                        </caption>
                                    </ref>
                                </figDesc>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div n="Text" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Eng" xml:lang="en">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Accipiter Palumbarius</foreign>: The Pigeon-Hawk.</p>
                        <p n="1">It weighs six ounces: the Bill at the point black, at the basis whitish; the Iris of the eye
                            yellow: the Basis of the upper mandible is cover’d with a yellow Sear: all the upper part of the Body,
                            Wings and Tail is brown: the interior vanes of the quill-feathers have large red spots: the Tail is
                            transversly marked with four white lines; the Throat, Breast and Belly white, intermix’d with brown
                            feathers; the small feathers that cover the thighs, reach within half an inch of the feet, and are
                            white, with a tincture of red, beset with long spots of brown; the Legs and Feet yellow. It is a very
                            swift and bold Hawk, preying on Pigeons and wild Turkeys while they are young.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div n="Fra" xml:lang="fr">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Accipiter Palumbarius</foreign>: Epervier à pigeons.</p>
                        <p n="1">Cet oiseau pese six onces. Il a la pointe du bec noire, &amp; la base blanchâtre; l’iris de
                            l’oeil jaune: la base de la mandibule superieure est courvert d’une peau jaune; tout le haut du corps,
                            les ailes, &amp; la queüe sont brunes. Les barbes interieures des plumes de l’aile ont de grandes
                            taches rouges. La queüe est marquée de quatre rayes blanches en travers; la gorge, la poitrine, &amp;
                            le ventre sont blancs, entremêtés de plumes brunes; les petites plumes equi couvrent les cuiffes vont
                            jusqu’à un demi pouce des piés &amp; sont blanches, avec une teinture de rouge, environnées de longues
                            taches brunes; les jambes &amp; les piés sont jaunes. C’est un épervier fort vite &amp; fort hardi; il
                            enleve les pigeons, &amp; même les dindons sauvages lors qu’ils sont jeunes.</p>

                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <!--
            <div n="X" type="section">
                <div n="Plate" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Figure">
                        <p n="FigX">
                            <figure>
                                <figDesc facs="urn:whole plate">
                                    <ref
                                        facs="urn:label-subsection-of-image">
                                        <caption>
                                            Catpion
                                        </caption>
                                    </ref>
                                    
                                </figDesc>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div n="Text" type="subsection">
                    <div n="Eng" xml:lang="en">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Latin Name</foreign>: English Name.</p>
                        <p n="1">English text</p>
                    </div>
                    <div n="Fra" xml:lang="fr">
                        <p n="H"><foreign xml:lang="la">Latin Name</foreign>: French Name.</p>
                        <p n="1">French text.</p>
                        
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            -->

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
